Résumé of Bill Lubanovic 1380 Wilderness Run Road, Eagan MN 55123

bill@madscheme.com

### Summary

Experienced full-stack developer of Linux/web/database services, tools, and APIs. O'Reilly author.

### **Publications**

#### **Books**

Introducing Python (Bill Lubanovic)

Linux System Administration (Tom Adelstein and Bill Lubanovic)

C'Reilly, 2014

O'Reilly, 2007

C'Reilly, 2007

O'Reilly, 2005

Building Secure Servers With Linux (Michael D Bauer) [contributor]

O'Reilly, 2002

# **Articles**

Python 3: Threat or Menace? Migrating Web-Based PHP Applications to Ajax The Lighttpd Web Server radar.oreilly.com, 2014 onlamp.com, 2007 onlamp.com, 2007

### **Awards**

Linux Journal – Favorite Linux Book: Linux System Administration

2008

## **Work History**

CrowdStrike (2016-2018) - Senior Software Engineer

Write internal web services and APIs for billions of daily endpoint events.

Systems: Linux (Ubuntu). Python, Pyramid, Tornado, Kafka, ZeroMQ, AWS, Docker.

Data: PostgreSQL, Redis, Cassandra, ElasticSearch, REST, RPC.

### Internet Archive (2015-2016) - Senior Software Engineer

Rewrite Wayback Machine and APIs in Python.

Systems: Linux (Ubuntu), Python, Flask, Ansible, uWSGI, gUnicorn, nginx, React.

Data: Redis, WARC, ElasticSearch.

# Penguin Computing (2014-2015) – Senior Software Engineer

Integrate OpenStack for high performance computing.

Systems: Linux (Ubuntu, CentOS), Python, OpenStack, Ansible.

Data: MvSQL. Redis.

# **Cray Inc** (2013-2014) - Contractor

Incorporate OpenStack into supercomputer systems.

Systems: Linux (SuSE, CentOS), Python, OpenStack, Docker, Ansible, VirtualBox.

Data: MySQL.

### Thomson Reuters (2013-2013) - Senior Software Engineer

Develop prototypes and proofs-of-concept for FindLaw's legal/web applications.

Systems: Linux, Python, PHP.

Web: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, AngularJS, Bootstrap.

Data: MySQL, Solr, MarkLogic, Hadoop.

### Keep Holdings (2010-2013) - Senior Software Engineer

Design and build stable, scalable Core Services for startup (adkeeper.com, keep.com).

Build consumer site back end (servers, services), middle (APIs), and front end (web UI).

Build admin site (exception handling, graphing, data editing, visualization).

Systems: Linux, Python, ZeroMQ, Sentry, Munin, AWS, Rackspace.

Web: Flask, nginx, uwsgi, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, jQuery, JSON, AJAX.

Data: Redis, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Cassandra.

### Intradyn (2008-2010) - Lead Developer

Write web-based dashboards of server and application usage.

Develop interactive complex searches for an email appliance.

Port a Ruby PXE installer to Python.

Systems: Linux, Python, RabbitMQ.

Web: Django, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, jQuery, Flot.

Data: PostgreSQL, Lucene.

# WindLogics (2005-2008) - Senior Software Engineer

Write web-based dashboards of wind energy forecasts and usage.

Systems: Linux, PHP, Python.

Web: PHP, iQuery, Flot.

Data: Weather data (satellite and files).

# Mad Scheme (1999-2005) - President

President and co-founder of Internet development and hosting company.

Develop commercial web sites and databases.

Manage servers and applications in multiple data centers.

Web and security consulting for financial companies.

Systems: Linux, C, perl, djbdns, qmail.

Web: Apache, Lighttpd, PHP, HTML, JavaScript.

Data: MySQL.

### WAM!NET (1995-1999) - Internet Services Manager

Write web-based dashboards to track file delivery on prepress network.

Develop 3M's Digital Media Repository.

Manage Internet applications group.

Systems: IRIX, Solaris, C.

Web: Apache, HTML, JavaScript.

Data: MySQL.

# **Tela** (1994-1995) – Vice President

Co-founder of early ISP.

Perform Internet/web seminars.

### Northwest Airlines (1990-1995) - Senior Developer

Write RAIDER graphic yield management system (generated millions in revenue over 10+ years).

Get NWA on the Internet. Demonstrate the Net and web to management in 1993.

Perform NWA's first web survey in 1994.

Lead C++ development team.

Systems: C, C++, X/Motif, Sybase, AIX.

### Dicomed (1988-1990) - Senior Programmer Analyst

Write graphics code in C and assembler for a digital film recorder.

Intran (1982-1988) - Software Engineer

Co-author MetaForm, one of the first GUI applications (before the Mac or Windows).

Systems: Pascal, C, microcode, PERQ (POS, ACCENT, PNX), Sun (SunOS), X.

### **Technical Experience**

Systems: Linux, UNIX (Solaris, IRIX, HP-UX, AIX, BSD, others).

Languages: Python, C, JavaScript, PHP, Perl; some Golang

Databases: Relational - MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQLite, SQLAlchemy, Sybase, Informix, DB/2, Oracle

NoSQL -- Redis, Cassandra, Memcache, ElasticSearch

Web: Client: HTML, JavaScript, jQuery, AJAX, JSON, CSS, Flot, Bootstrap, AngularJS

Server: Apache, CGI, WSGI, uWSGI, Flask, Django, Lighttpd, Nginx

Other: Messages/events (ZeroMQ, gevent. Kafka), Graphics/UI (X/Motif), Mapping

#### Education

Ph.D. Work (1973-1980, not completed) – University of Minnesota, Physiology

B.S. (1969-1973) – University of Pittsburgh, Biology